Usually, I'd add a preamble where you
decide if you'll stick around or if you
think that I've insufferable, but
nothing gets in the way of chocolate.
Believe it or not, although I'd find it
preferable if you did, chocolate can be
healthy for you. Can because it really
depends on a number of factors that
we'll get into, including how some
chocolates are toxic. No joke. So, what
makes chocolate so healthy? Didn't think
that those words would be paired
together. Chocolate healthy. Well,
certain chocolates contain appreciable
amounts of flavonols and polyphenols.
Those are fancy terms for molecules that
improve your cardiovascular health,
brain health, and even have been linked
to reducing insulin resistance, like
type 2 diabetes. You don't need to take
my word for it. There's plenty of
evidence like that described in this
review. Now, in slightly more detail,
these molecules do a number of things to
our body. One, they act as antioxidants,
which means that as your cells produce
different potentially destructive
molecules called free radicals, they can
interact with these molecules and
neutralize them. In addition, these
chocolate married molecules, these
flavonols and polyphenols also increase
the amount of a potent molecule called
nitric oxide. Now, cells that line your
blood vessels produce more nitric oxide
when exposed in greater number of these
chocolate linked molecules. And nitric
oxide relaxes the blood vessel thereby
reducing blood pressure. Okay, one more
for good measure. Chocolate also seems
to reduce the blood cholesterol levels
which are heavily implicated in heart
disease. It does that through a number
of mechanisms but one of the cooler ones
is through reducing cholesterol uptake
in the intestines as well as reducing
the gene expression of enzymes involved
in cholesterol synthesis in your liver.
Now, keep in mind I'm limiting this. So,
there's plenty more to discuss. I'll do
that in future content. For now, let's
just say that there are many ways that
these molecules in chocolate benefit us.
Again, that depends on some factors. And
one of those factors is if the same
chocolate is also filled with toxic
metals. Unfortunately, many of the
chocolates also come with a healthy or
maybe I should say unhealthy dose of
metals like cadmium and lead. These
metals are toxic as they accumulate in
your organs, especially your kidneys,
your bones, and your brain. Once there,
they compete with essential nutrients
like calcium and zinc, and also
interfere with DNA repair as well as
protein folding, which means that the
cells no longer able to produce
functional proteins that serve a purpose
in the body. That's a big deal,
especially when discussing low
replicating cells like those in your
brain. The currently deemed acceptable
amount of cadmium per day is less than
25 micrograms per day. And the current
deemed acceptable amount of lead is
absolutely zero. And yet many chocolates
contain upward of 10 or 15 micrograms
per serving and even some lead and even
arsenic. So eating just one or two
servings can already set you up to
exceed acceptable amounts in your body.
That's not even to consider the
vulnerable populations like pregnant
women. So assuming that you did find
chocolates without and I'll mention some
in a bit. There's two more
considerations in relation to chocolate.
One, it has to be dark chocolate. The
sweeter chocolates tend to be a filled
with more sugar and b tend to have very
low levels of these flavonols and
polyphenols that we briefly discussed.
The cut off for dark chocolate is around
70%. Anything higher is likely better.
The second consideration is a particular
type of processing called dutching or
undutching. Essentially, Dutch chocolate
is less acidic, more neutral than
undutched chocolate. Aside from reading
the label, you can also just taste the
difference. Dutched chocolate is less
bitter. And undutched is not only more
bitter, but sharper and fruier in taste.
Unfortunately, Dutch chocolate, although
it tastes better to many, it is
significantly reduced in polyphenol and
flavonol amounts, sometimes up to 90%,
has been eliminated. So, essentially,
Dutch chocolate is worthless for health
benefits. Another way to tell, which
might confuse some people, is the fact
that undutched chocolate, the type that
we want, is lighter in color. So, the
darker the chocolate looks, although
it's dark chocolate, may actually mean
it's Dutch. Anyway, enough bad mouthing
the Dutch. I'm going to offer you a few
recommendations for undutched safe dark
chocolates in a minute. But I also offer
many more options and some potent
alternatives to chocolate and another
few minor factors to consider in the
extended version of this video that
you're watching available for the
Physionic Insiders. I have a list of
approved chocolates as substitutes, and
you get access to my entire library of
videos, written research reviews, short
summaries on everything, a podcast, live
sessions with my undutch self, and more.
The link to join is in the description
box. I hope to see you there. Okay.
Although there are many dark chocolates
that are poor quality and unfortunately
they're all over the supermarket, here
are two that have been independently lab
tested for very low cadmium levels and
virtually no lead in them that have also
a rich flavonol profile. Oh, also I have
no affiliation with these brands. Here
they are. Baker's unsweetened 100% cacao
and Lily's dark ch or extra dark
chocolate 70%. Now, if you can't bear
the bitterness, you could try the 70%.
So, in the end, aim for dark, undutch
chocolate that is not contaminated with
high levels of cadmium, lead, and
arsenic because that chocolate has been
shown to improve multiple health
outcomes like those I discuss here.
Thanks for watching.